<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Mehmet Sat | Personal Blog</title><link>https://mehmetsat.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Mehmet Sat | Personal Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mehmetsat.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data Wrangling with PySpark</title><link>https://mehmetsat.github.io/homepage/data-wrangling-with-pyspark/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mehmetsat.github.io/homepage/data-wrangling-with-pyspark/</guid><description>It becomes very hard to work with pandas when the data is huge. Instead as a strong alternative PySpark comes along. In this tutorial I will introduce the PySpark and mirror our pandas abilities to PySpark. This post assumes the reader has familiarity with the pandas library.
Introduction to Spark The first question is what is Spark. Apache Spark is fast and general engine for large-scale data processing. It distributes computations among the CPU cores to do parallel processing.</description></item><item><title>Recommendation Engines Overview</title><link>https://mehmetsat.github.io/homepage/recommendation-engines-overview/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mehmetsat.github.io/homepage/recommendation-engines-overview/</guid><description>In these days, for customers there are so many alternatives to use a mobile app for a specific task and most of them work well in terms of functionality. What differs in terms of the customer is the experience you gave them. The most powerful influence that you can give to the customer is making them feel special. To do this you must provide a personalized experience for each customer. Recommendation Engines are exactly developed on that purpose.</description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://mehmetsat.github.io/homepage/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mehmetsat.github.io/homepage/about/</guid><description>I am a Data Scientist who has a strong technical background as an Electrical Engineer. I have decided to continue my career in Data Science and working in that field over 2 years which is related to my interest areas Natural Language Processing and Recommendation Engines. My objective is to learn every step of developing a Machine Learning Model from how data has stored and managed to which model is used and monitoring its success in the real life.</description></item></channel></rss>